# Jeff W. Bell

# Educator

40 College Hill Road Rothesay N.B. E2E 5H1 +1 506 654 1230 jeffbell.27@gmail.com

# **Overview**

I am a caring educator with quality leadership experience in multiple school domains, and possess a high drive for learning and a passion to incorporate new ideas into my teaching practice. I have a wide range of teachable skills that include Grades 6-12 Math and Science fields, and am currently spending my time focusing on learning and creating Computer Programming academic courses. Outside of the classroom I enjoy working with students on interpersonal skills and teach yoga as a way to stay healthy.

# **EXPERIENCE**

# Rothesay Netherwood School - Science Department Head

July 2018 - Present

- Managed largest academic budget at school:
  - Addressed both inventory maintenance and growth opportunities.
  - Worked closely with teachers to order equipment and consumables based on need.
- Curricular & Instructional oversight:
  - Practiced consistent dialogue with department teachers on best practices.
  - Helped new teachers become comfortable with the environment and courses.
  - Made recommendations to the Head of Academics on class sizes and departmental needs.
- Interpersonal skills and staff placement:
  - Ensured that staff could deliver excellent instruction by managing the number of class preps and level of course difficulty given to them.
  - Accommodating approach to course selection since becoming department head (I always chose my own classes last!)

- Brainstormed solutions to problems and created new initiatives:
  - Regularly helped with and discussed interdepartmental issues such as timetable, staffing, and common tools for academic delivery.
  - Currently pushing for cultural awareness and strong anti-racist training at our school.
- Assisted with Development of New Academic Science Building:
  - Meetings concerned physical space requirements of new academic building.
  - Future planning for lab-spaces and researched companies for lab-build tenders.
  - Was consistently called upon for quick reference during the build, and researched best practice for lab design during the process.
  - Great experience for further understanding the donation structures and bottom line of independent schools.

# Rothesay Netherwood School - Residential Houseparent

July 2017 - Present

- Managed 30 local and international students a year in the Kirk House Dormitory:
  - Provided emotional support for students on a daily basis.
  - Acted as guardian for students away from home.
  - Ensured that parents were well-involved with their child's development, including consistent dialogue in an effort of 'co-parenting'.
  - Managed both girls and boys in a co-ed facility (2019-2020).
- Worked outside of regular school hours:
  - Schedule encompassed supervision from morning wake up to final night-time rounds (15+ hour days).
  - Provided parental guidance and structured activities on weekends.
- Managed a house budget:
  - o Ensured that common student needs were met.
  - Autonomously operated the budget.
  - Planned celebratory outings and events through the year (Movie theatre night & pizza parties).

•

# Rothesay Netherwood School - Faculty

September 2015 - PRESENT

- General Faculty Roles
  - Creation of 3 Effort Reports per year (non-numeric report card).

- Creation of 3 Cumulative Reports per year (included numerical grade and a specific comment for each student).
- Attendance at numerous events outside of regular work hours.
- Commitment to academic and extracurricular programs.
- Advisor to a group of High School students.

#### Grade 9 Computer Engineering

- Developed Computer Engineering (Grade 9) course from scratch.
- Taught the Python programming language.
- Proposed, purchased, and managed a class set of Raspberry Pi computers.
- Integrated Python programming to Raspberry Pi's.
- Created several major projects that included game development, web development, and physical computing.
- Created assignments and rubrics that accurately reflected the different levels of programmers in the course.
- Currently developing the follow-up Grade 10 course.

## IB Physics (1 Year)

- Prepared students for IB exam.
- Guided students and marked final products for the IB Internal Assessment project.
- IB Math (1 Year, Pre-2020 Curriculum)
  - Prepared students for IB exam.
  - Guided students and marked final products for the IB Mathematical Exploration project.

#### IB Chemistry (3 Years)

- Well-practiced lab work both in-lab and online.
- Flipped-classroom units and self-made YouTube videos for instruction.
- o Prepared students for test-specific IB tasks.

# • IB Biology (1 Year)

- Well-practiced lab work both in-lab and online.
- Flipped-classroom units and continuous online formative assessments.
- Prepared students for test-specific IB tasks.

#### Grade 10 Math (3 Years)

- o IB MYP Mathematics program, preparing for IB DP Programme.
- Established a continuous routine of 'scoreless' formative assessments.
- Created summative assessments in line with the expectations of the IB programme.

# Grade 10 Science (1 Year)

Taught the biology of basic genetics and evolution.

- Carefully scaffolded all information to lead to an ultimate discussion on sex, gender, gender roles, and expansion of the traditional gender binary using scientific evidence.
- Grade 9 Science (2 Years)
  - Taught basic cell biology, atoms and molecules, kinematics, and electricity.
  - Incorporated many hands on activities and physical demonstrations.
  - Used student-based models as frequently as possible (either mental models or physical builds).

# Rothesay Netherwood School - Residential Houseparent

July 2017 - Present

- Managed 30 local and international students a year in the Kirk House Dormitory:
  - Counselled individual students on a daily basis.
  - Acted as guardian for students away from home.
  - Ensured that parents were well-involved with their child's development, including consistent dialogue in an effort of 'co-parenting'.
  - Managed both girls and boys in a co-ed facility (2019-2020).
- Worked outside of regular school hours:
  - Schedule encompassed supervision from morning wake up to final night-time rounds (15+ hour days).
  - Provided parental guidance and structured activities on weekends.
- -Managed a house budget:
  - Ensured that common student needs were met.
  - Autonomously operated the budget.
  - Planned celebratory outings and events through the year
    (Movie theatre night & pizza parties).

#### Rothesay Netherwood School - Extracurricular Activities

September 2015 - Present

- Coached hockey at various levels:
  - Head Coach of recreational Midget 'C' team (2015-2016).
  - Assistant Coach of Varsity Girls Team (2016-2018):
    - Included consistent travel.
    - Helped manage logistics involved with travelling internationally for competition.
- Fitness Supervisor (2018 Present)
  - Helped with the health and wellness of students after school in the fitness centre.

- Developed individual plans and assisted with proper technique and advice.
- Yoga Instructor (2017 Present)
  - 200-HR YTT yoga certification holder.
  - Delivered yoga classes to school classes, groups and teams, as well as the general public.

# **Skills**

- Critical Thinker.
- Compassionate Care.
- Technologically competent:
  - Well-versed with GSuite technologies, and integrating into a
    1-to-1 student laptop classroom. (Microsoft Suite & GSuite)
  - Experienced with Python, R, JavaScript, HTML, CSS, and Linux programming languages with integration to the Raspberry Pi.
- Certified IB teacher (Category 2, Chemistry)
- Experienced with IB rigors and program requirements.
- Flexible teachable subjects.

# **EDUCATION & Certification**

# Mount Allison University, Sackville, NB - B.Sc. Biology (Honors)

January 2010 - April 2014

- Biology Major
- Chemistry Minor
- Honors Research Thesis covered the movement patterns of Juvenile Atlantic Sturgeon in the Saint John River, NB.

# St. Thomas University, Fredericton, NB- B.Ed. General Sciences

September 2014 - June 2015

- Middle / High School Science & Math Stream.
- High School teaching practicum at Bernice MacNaughton High School (Moncton, NB).
- Middle School teaching practicum at Riverview Middle School (Riverview, NB).

•

# Always-at-Aum Yoga School - Rothesay/New York - YTT - 200HR

February 2017

- Yoga training catered to many domains of health and wellness.
- Focused on: yoga for kids, yoga for athletes, and yoga for the general public.

# -References available upon request-